{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This non-President claimed that John Henrie Kagi was his \"Secretary of War.\" Victor Hugo said that this man's death would be like \"Washington killing Spartacus.\" This man was funded by the Secret Six, which included Thomas Higginson. On the morning of his execution in Virginia, he wrote that \"the crimes of this guilty land will never be purged away but with blood.\" For 10 points, name this radical abolitionist who led a failed 1859 raid at Harpers Ferry.",
      "answer": "John Brown <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man wrote a play from the perspective of Ernst Rohm titled “My Friend Hitler.” This man was accompanied by the Tatenokai during a raid on the headquarters of the Ground Self- Defense Force. His homosexuality inspired him to write Confessions of a Mask. This author wrote about Mizoguchi setting a Buddhist temple in Kyoto on fire. For 10 points, name this author of The Temple of the Golden Pavilion who committed seppuku after a failed coup attempt in 1970.",
      "answer": "Yukio Mishima <KG> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This group was the plaintiff in a Supreme Court case involving T.I.M.E.-D.C., Inc. This group’s investigation by the Senate’s McClellan Committee prompted the imprisonment of Dave Beck, who had succeeded Dan Tobin as president. This union was expelled from the AFL-CIO in 1957, the same year it elected a president who disappeared in 1975. Jimmy Hoffa led, for 10 points, what union whose membership includes truck drivers?",
      "answer": "International Brotherhood of Teamsters, Chauffeurs, Warehousemen, and Helpers of America <SH> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "An account of this event describes a column of smoke “like an umbrella pine.” An observer of this event was told of it by Rectina, which prompted him to dispatch ships to Resina. This event destroyed the town of Stabiae. It was described in letters by Pliny the Younger, and its victims were preserved by the ash that buried them. For 10 points, name this 79 CE disaster that destroyed Herculaneum and Pompeii.",
      "answer": "eruption of Mount Vesuvius <SH> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Adherents of this religion believe that in the afterlife, one is classified into one of three degrees of glory. The ultimate goal in this religion is a God-like state called exaltation. Members of this religion drew ire for baptizing dead Holocaust victims. With the exception of some fundamentalist sects, this religious group has outlawed polygamy. For 10 points, name this religion whose members followed Brigham Young to Utah.",
      "answer": "Mormonism <AK> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 6"
    },
    {
      "question": "During a tuberculosis outbreak in this state, Mercy Brown was accused of being a vampire. In the waters off the coast of this state, the Sons of Liberty attacked and burned William Duddington's ship during the Gaspee Affair. This state did not attend the Constitutional Convention and became the last of the original Thirteen Colonies to ratify the Constitution. For 10 points, name this state whose official name includes the phrase \"Providence Plantations.\"",
      "answer": "Rhode Island <KG> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Michele Luzoro has continued a tradition of producing this good in the town of Biot along the French Riviera. Since the 1300s, a center for producing this good on Murano island has kept its methods secretive within the Venice lagoon. In pre-industrial times, this material was shaped out of molten materials such as soda-lime by \"blowing\" air through a pipe. For 10 points, name this translucent amorphous solid which was stained with colors for use in cathedral windows.",
      "answer": "glass <MJ> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This legislation was a major feature of the pre-March, or Vormarz, era. This legislation was partly inspired by the book-burnings carried out at the Wartburg Festival. The impetus for this legislation was Karl Sand's assassination of August von Kotzebue. These laws banned nationalist fraternities called Burschenschaften. For 10 points, name this set of decrees which cracked down on freedom of speech and were issued by Klemens von Metternich.",
      "answer": "Carlsbad Decrees <JB> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "Francois Arago suggested naming this body after its discoverer, although names such as Janus were proposed. Johann Galle was the first person to observe this body, although its existence had been predicted by John Couch Adams and Urbain Le Verrier. Some scientists believed there lay a further \"Planet X\" beyond it. Before its discovery, this planet's existence was theorized due to irregularities in the orbit of Uranus. For 10 points, name this farthest planet from the Sun.",
      "answer": "Neptune <JL> {I}"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man formed a party called The People of Freedom, which dissolved in November 2013. A Moroccan named Karima El Mahroug, also known as Ruby Rubacuori, was implicated in a trial of this leader for soliciting underage sex workers. This owner of the Mediaset company threw indecent \"bunga bunga\" parties while leading his country. For 10 points, name this brusque Italian billionaire who preceded Mario Monti in his most recent term as Prime Minister.",
      "answer": "Silvio Berlusconi <MJ> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 6"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man signed the Franklin-Bouillon Agreement with the French, from whom he later acquired the Republic of Hatay. Reformism and Statism were among this leader's Six Arrows. This leader said \"I order you to die\" to his troops while leading the defending forces in the Gallipoli Campaign. This predecessor of Ismet Inonu introduced the Latin alphabet and banned the fez. For 10 points, name this first president of Turkey.",
        "answer": "Mustafa Kemal Ataturk"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The borders of Ataturk's Turkey were set by what 1923 treaty named for a city in Switzerland, which superseded the harsher Treaty of Sevres?",
        "answer": "Treaty of Lausanne <JB> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A scandal involving mass purchase of this material involved Abel Corbin, who had the ear of the sitting United States president. In 19th-century American politics, this material was the \"1\" in a 16-to-1 ratio advocated for by many populists. On September 24, 1869, James Fisk and Jay Gould cornered the market by buying up this substance on what is now called Black Friday. For 10 points, name this coinage metal whose \"standard\" was abandoned for US currency in 1973.",
        "answer": "gold"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Thomas Carlyle coined what two-word pejorative, which magazines like Atlantic Monthly started using in the 1870s to denote corrupt industry executives such as Jay Gould?",
        "answer": "\"robber barons\" <MJ> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One kingdom of this people collapsed after being defeated at the Battle of Guadalete. This people established a capital at Toulouse under Euric and were later limited to Spain after losing to Clovis I at Vouille (pr. voo-EEL). They used the Liber Iudiciorum law code in their kingdom in Spain. One leader of this people went to war against Honorius and sacked Rome in 410 AD. For 10 points, name this tribe which separated from the Ostrogoths.",
        "answer": "Visigoths"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which first King of the Visigoths fought at the Battle of the Frigidus and later led the Sack of Rome in 410 AD?",
        "answer": "Alaric <JZ> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "In 2009, this state became the first to legislate same sex marriage. A one-time governor of this state proposed the 50-State Strategy as chairman of the DNC. That politician from this state, who made a famous “scream” after losing the 2004 Iowa Democratic Caucus, was Howard Dean. This state is the home of the longest serving independent congressman in U.S. history. For 10 points, name New England state whose Senator Bernie Sanders was once mayor of Burlington.",
        "answer": "Vermont"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What Massachusetts senator defeated Howard Dean to win the 2004 Democratic nomination for president?",
        "answer": "John Kerry <ED> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 6"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Legislation promoted by this man replaced the Laws of Burgos. This man argued with Juan de Sepulveda at the Valladolid (pr. vie-uh-DOE-leed) Debate. This person controversially argued for the importation of African slaves and advocated for the New Laws. His \"Account of the Destruction of the Indies\" denounced the encomienda system. For 10 points, name this friar who argued for the rights of Native Americans in the Spanish Empire.",
        "answer": "Bartolome de las Casas"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Las Casas belonged to what order of friars, whose members often combated heresy by participating in the inquisition?",
        "answer": "Dominican Order <JB> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The speaker of this speech signed a resolution later that afternoon while wearing a black armband. After this speech was given, a vote in Congress passed 388 to 1 over the sole objection of Jeannette Rankin, the first woman in Congress. It listed Guam and Wake Island among locations targeted the previous day. For 10 points, identify this FDR speech given the day after the attack on Pearl Harbor, which is named after the nickname it gave to December 7th.",
        "answer": "day of infamy speech"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Day of Infamy speech was attended by a widow of which President, the last before FDR to ask Congress for a declaration of war?",
        "answer": "Woodrow Wilson <VP> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Fresnel and Stokes proposed distinct models for this substance's namesake drag. The Trouton- Noble experiment attempted to prove the existence of this substance. An attempt to find this substance failed to measure a significant fringe shift and involved using an interferometer to split light beams. Its existence was disproved by the Michelson-Morley experiment. For 10 points, name this substance once thought to be the medium through which light passes.",
        "answer": "luminiferous aether"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Trouton-Noble experiment tracked the motion of what kind of device, which was derived from the earlier Leyden jar?",
        "answer": "parallel-plate capacitor <KG> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "An incident in this war was the subject of a question asked by schoolteacher Diana Gould. One side during this conflict used Exocet missiles to sink the Atlantic Conveyer. The Battle of Goose Green during this conflict featured an attack on Darwin hill, while other clashes saw the sinking of the Sheffield and the General Belgrano. It ended with the capture of Stanley. For 10 points, name this war where Argentina was defeated by Britain in a conflict over namesake Atlantic islands.",
        "answer": "Falkland Islands War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which isolated Atlantic island, named for a Christian holiday, was an important staging area for the war at its Wideawake Airfield?",
        "answer": "Ascension Island <JZ> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 6"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Four leaders of this group visited England for a meeting arranged by Peter Schuyler and had their portraits painted by Jan Verelst. John Sullivan led a campaign that destroyed this group's lands. Leaders of this group included Joseph Brandt, and it was founded by the Great Peacemaker and Hiawatha. This group was an important native polity in the 18th century in what is now Western New York. For 10 points, name this confederacy of Native American tribes, which included the Seneca and Mohawk tribes.",
        "answer": "Iroquois Confederacy"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Iroquois fought a war against the French named after what animal, whose fur trade was important in the seventeenth century?",
        "answer": "beaver <JL> {I}"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This deity gave a mandate to a son and grandson to rule the \"central land of the Reed Plains.\" This deity spawned three children by eating a sword as part of a sibling rivalry. A mirror legendarily placed in a tree to lure out this deity is now in a set of Three Imperial Regalia first given to Ninigi, which includes beads and the Kusanagi blade wielded by her brother Susano'o. For 10 points, name this sun goddess who is claimed as an ancestor by all emperors of Japan.",
        "answer": "Amaterasu-omikami"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What legendary great-grandson of Amaterasu, who was guided by a three-legged crow, is regarded as the first emperor of Japan?",
        "answer": "Jimmu-tenno <MJ> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 6"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "LYNDON BAINES JOHNSON:",
      "prompt": "Name the lyndon baines johnson:...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was a Senator from which Lone Star State?",
          "answer": "Texas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Succeeded which assassinated President?",
          "answer": "John Fitzgerald Kennedy"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was inaugurated inside which vehicle at Love Airfield?",
          "answer": "Air Force One"
        },
        {
          "question": "Signed which 1964 legislation outlawing race based discrimination?",
          "answer": "Civil Rights Act of 1964"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attacked poverty and racial injustice in which program which created Medicare and Medicaid?",
          "answer": "“Great Society”"
        },
        {
          "question": "Appointed which Supreme Court justice later forced to resign due to ethics violations?",
          "answer": "Abraham “Abe” Fortas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Almost lost which state’s 1968 primary to Eugene McCarthy, prompting McCarthy’s withdrawal from the race?",
          "answer": "New Hampshire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was succeeded as Senate Majority Leader by which Montanan?",
          "answer": "Mike Mansfield <JZ> {I}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "CURRENT WORLD LEADERS:",
      "prompt": "Which current world leader…",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Is Prime Minister of the UK and is up for election in May?",
          "answer": "David Cameron"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was elected Prime Minister of Canada in 2006?",
          "answer": "Stephen Harper"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is the first female Chancellor of Germany?",
          "answer": "Angela Merkel"
        },
        {
          "question": "Defeated Congress to become Prime Minister of India in 2014?",
          "answer": "Narendra Modi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Is Prime Minister of Japan and namesake of an economic policy?",
          "answer": "Shinzo Abe"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was commander in chief of Egypt’s armed forces before being elected President?",
          "answer": "Abdel Fattah el-Sisi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Succeeded Felipe Calderon as President of Mexico?",
          "answer": "Enrique Peña Nieto"
        },
        {
          "question": "Has been Prime Minister of Jamaica since 2012?",
          "answer": "Portia Simpson-Miller <TR> {I}"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "HENRY V",
      "prompt": "Name the henry v...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the son of which previous monarch?",
          "answer": "Henry IV"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was a member of which house opposed to the House of York?",
          "answer": "Lancaster"
        },
        {
          "question": "Won which major battle over the French on St. Crispin’s Day, 1415?",
          "answer": "Battle of Agincourt"
        },
        {
          "question": "According to Shakespeare, was friends with which fictional buffoon?",
          "answer": "Sir John Falstaff"
        },
        {
          "question": "Failed to capture which leader of the Welsh Revolt?",
          "answer": "Owen Glendower"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was wounded at which battle against the rebel Henry Hotspur?",
          "answer": "Battle of Shrewsbury"
        },
        {
          "question": "Thwarted which 1415 conspiracy against him named for a port city?",
          "answer": "Southampton Plot"
        },
        {
          "question": "Died during a siege of which French town?",
          "answer": "Meaux pr. Moe <TR> {I}"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The law at the center of this court case was earlier broken by Daniel Desdunes. Samuel F. Phillips took part in this case, defending the plaintiff. A Citizen's Committee raised money to hire Albion (20 pts)",
        "Tourgee as the attorney for this case's plaintiff. The line \"the law regards man as man\" was written as part of the lone dissent in this case, by John Marshall (10 pts)",
        "Harlan. The plaintiff in this case was detained for intentionally boarding a whites-only railcar, despite being only one-eighth black. For 10 points, name this Supreme Court case that established the doctrine of \"separate but equal.\""
      ],
      "answer": "Plessy v. Ferguson <JL> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One concerto by this man was premiered by Anton Stadler and was originally written for basset horn. A piano concerto by this man was played at the ceremony where Leopold II was named Holy Roman Emperor, giving it the nickname (20 pts)",
        "“Coronation.” This composer of an early Clarinet Concerto imitated the sound of Janissary bands in the finale of his eleventh (10 pts)",
        "piano sonata. His final symphony ends with a five-voice fugue and was nicknamed by Johann Salomon. For 10 points, name this composer of the Jupiter Symphony and “Rondo Alla Turca.”"
      ],
      "answer": "Wolfgang Amadeus Mozart <CW> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In a court case dealing with this state, Archibald Cox quipped that Harvard did not do well at sports. The founder of the American Civil Rights Institute, Ward Connerly, was largely based in this state whose Proposition 209, which was emulated in (20 pts)",
        "Michigan, sought to eliminate affirmative action in public employment. A medical school here was the subject of the 1978 Bakke decision, which (10 pts)",
        "ruled specific racial quotas in admissions were impermissible. For 10 points, name this western state, whose university system includes campuses at Davis and Irvine."
      ],
      "answer": "California <MC> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man is often mistakenly credited for piloting the first airplane flight in Australia. This man often performed with his younger brother, Theodore Hardeen. This man decried a performer named Margery after the death of his (20 pts)",
        "mother inspired him to debunk seances and mediums. This man, a Hungarian immigrant born as Erik (10 pts)",
        "Weisz (pr. VICE), originated the routine called the Chinese Water Torture Cell, in which he was placed upside down into a water-filled tank. For 10 points, name this entertainer who escaped from straitjackets, sealed milk cans, and other dangerous scenarios."
      ],
      "answer": "Harry Houdini <KG> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A faction opposed to this treaty attempted to reverse it by assassinating Count Mirbach and launching the Left SR uprising. Prince Frederick Charles of Hesse and Wilhelm of Urach became monarchs by this treaty. One of the parties in this treaty pursued a policy of \"no war, (20 pts)",
        "no peace\" by stalling negotiations. This treaty was renounced by the latter Treaty of Rapallo, and it was negotiated between delegations led by Richard (10 pts)",
        "von Kuhlmann and Leon Trotsky. For 10 points, name this 1918 treaty which allowed the Soviet Union to exit World War I."
      ],
      "answer": "Treaty of Brest-Litovsk <JB> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 6"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The BeltLine is a former rail line being developed as a trail around this city. This city’s northern suburbs include the former Milton County, which ceased to exist in 1931, and whose area includes Johns Creek and Roswell. Its northern suburb of Sandy (20 pts)",
        "Springs is home to the Perimeter Center business district. Clayton County, south of this city, recently voted to join its (10 pts)",
        "MARTA service area. This city is where the Weather Channel and CNN established their headquarters. For 10 points, name this city that hosted the 1996 Olympics, the largest in Georgia."
      ],
      "answer": "Atlanta, Georgia <CW> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "A building owned by this man was set alight with \"Greek Fire\" by a group of spies called the Confederate Army of Manhattan. This state congressman from Connecticut once used a sign reading \"this way to the egress\" to control crowds. This man promoted the (*) \"Swedish Nightingale,\" Jenny Lind, and bought an object created from a monkey and a fish (*), the \"Fiji Mermaid.\" This person is erroneously credited with the phrase, \"there's a sucker born every minute.\" For 10 points, name this hoaxer and showman who names a circus with John Bailey."
      ],
      "answer": "P. T. Barnum <JB> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Study of an artifact found at this site suggest that it was called Kukkutarma, or \"city of the cockerel,\" implying that it was the place where chickens were first domesticated. At this site, a small bronze figurine in the position of putting her hand to her hips while only wearing armlets was discovered and named Dancing (20 pts)",
        "Girl. A \"Great Granary\" and a \"Great Bath\" are located at this site's Citadel mound. This archeological site is (10 pts)",
        "located in the Sindh province in Pakistan. For 10 points, name this site, which like Harappa, was a city of the Indus Valley Civilization."
      ],
      "answer": "Mohenjo-Daro"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this musical, an argument about the need to make saltpeter briefly flares up between a woman and her husband. In this musical's opening song, demands to \"Open up a window!\" are rebutted with \"Too many flies! Too many flies!\" (20 pts)",
        "Rutledge imitates a slave auctioneer in its later song \"Molasses to Rum.\" At its end, a bell rings louder and louder as several men sign a roll of paper despite (10 pts)",
        "their earlier cries of \"Sit down\" directed at its protagonist, John Adams. For 10 points, name this musical by Sherman Edwards, set in the year in which the Declaration of Independence was drafted."
      ],
      "answer": "1776 <MJ> {I}"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) In this battle, Henry de Bohun attempted to charge the opposing side's leader, who promptly split de Bohun's head in half with an axe. Alexander Seton deserted one side in this battle, which featured a disastrous charge by the Earl of Gloucester (pr. GLOSS-ter), Gilbert de Clare. The victors at this battle issued the (20 pts)",
        "Declaration of Arbroath. The schiltron formation was used to great effect by one side in this battle, which ended when (10 pts)",
        "Edward II fled to Dunbar Castle and sailed back to England. For 10 points, name this 1314 battle in the First War of Scottish Independence, a decisive victory for Robert the Bruce."
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Bannockburn <CKM> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 6"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "An act of arson at this building occurred four weeks after Adolf Hitler became chancellor. For 10 points, name this building damaged by a 1933 fire, the home of the German parliament."
      ],
      "answer": "the Reichstag building <KG> {I} 2015 National History Bowl High School Championships Round 6"
    }
  ]
}